Salaam alaikum.
السلام عليكم
Welcome to Doha.
مرحبا بكم في الدوحة
I am in charge of making this country's food secure.
تقع على عاتقي مسؤلية الامن الغذائي لهذا البلد
That is my job for the next two years,
هذا سيكون عملي للسنتين القادمتين
to design an entire master plan,
لتصيميم خطة رئيسية بالكامل
and then for the next 10 years to implement it --
ولتنفيذها في السنوات العشر القادمة
of course, with so many other people.
بالطبع مع اشخاص اخرين كثر
But first, I need to talk to you about a story, which is my story,
و لكن في البدايه اريد التحدث معكم حول قصه ما والتي هي قصتي
about the story of this country that you're all here in today.
انها قصة هذا البلد الذي جميعكم فيه اليوم
And of course, most of you have had three meals today,
وبالطبع جميعكم قد تناولتم الوجبات الغذائيه الثلاث هذا اليوم
and probably will continue to have after this event.
وعلى الارجح انكم ستتناولون ايضا بعد هذه الفعاليه
So going in, what was Qatar in the 1940s?
اذا نستمر ، كيف كانت قطر في عام 1940
We were about 11,000 people living here.
كان تعدادنا السكاني 11,000يعيشون هنا
There was no water. There was no energy, no oil, no cars, none of that.
لم يكن هناك ماء، ولا طاقه ولانفط ولا سيارات لايوجد اي شئ من ذلك
Most of the people who lived here
معظم الناس الذين عاشوا هنا
either lived in coastal villages, fishing,
سواء على الساحل او في القرى او صيد الاسماك
or were nomads who roamed around with the environment trying to find water.
او البدو الذين يتنقلون في الجوار بحثا عن الماء.
None of the glamour that you see today existed.
ليس ايا من المغريات الحاليه كان موجودا
No cities like you see today in Doha or Dubai or Abu Dhabi or Kuwait or Riyadh.
لاتوجد مدن كالتي رأيت اليوم في الدوحه او دبي او ابو ظبي او الكويت او الرياض
It wasn't that they couldn't develop cities.
انهم لم يكونوا عاجزين عن تطوير المدن
Resources weren't there to develop them.
ولكن المصادر لم تكن موجوده لتطورهم
And you can see that life expectancy was also short.
اضافه الى ذلك توقعات الحياة كانت قصيره
Most people died around the age of 50.
معظم الناس كانوا يتوفون في عمر الـ 50
So let's move to chapter two: the oil era.
دعونا ننتقل الى الفصل الثاني : حقبة النفط
1939, that's when they discovered oil.
عام 1939 كان وقت اكتشاف النفط
But unfortunately, it wasn't really fully exploited commercially
ولكن لسوء الحظ لم يكن حقا مستغل بالكامل تجاريا
until after the Second World War.
الى ما بعد الحرب العالميه الثانيه
What did it do?
ماذا صنع ؟
It changed the face of this country, as you can see today and witness.
لقد قام بتغيير وجه هذا البلد كما تشاهدون اليوم
It also made all those people who roamed around the desert --
وقام ايضا بجعل كل هؤلاء الناس الذين يجوبون الصحراء
looking for water, looking for food,
بحثا عن الماء والكلأ
trying to take care of their livestock -- urbanize.
للعنايه بماشيتهم...يتحولون الى المدن
You might find this strange,
ربما تجدون هذا غريبا
but in my family we have different accents.
في عائلتي توجد اكثر من لهجه
My mother has an accent that is so different to my father,
لهجة والدتي تختلف تماما عن لهجة والدي
and we're all a population of about 300,000 people in the same country.
على الرغم من انا تعدادنا لايتجاوز ال 300,000 في البلد نفسه
There are about five or six accents in this country as I speak.
يوجد في هذا البلد بينما انا اتكلم الان 6 لهجات مختلفه
Someone says, "How so? How could this happen?"
ربما يقول قائل كيف لهذا ان يحدث؟
Because we lived scattered.
لئننا عشنا مشتتين
We couldn't live in a concentrated way simply because there was no resources.
لم نستطع العيش مجتمعين لعدم وجود المصادر.
And when the resources came, be it oil,
وعندما توفرت المصادر متمثلة بالنفط
we started building these fancy technologies
بدأنا ببناء هذه التكنولوجيا البارعه
and bringing people together because we needed the concentration.
وجمعنا الناس مع بعض بسبب حاجتنا لهذا الحشد
People started to get to know each other.
بدأ الناس بالتعرف الى بعضهم البعض
And we realized that there are some differences in accents.
وبدأنا بإدراك وجود اختلاف في اللهجات
So that is the chapter two: the oil era.
كان ذاك هو الفصل الثاني : حقبة النفط
Let's look at today.
لنلقي نظره على واقع اليوم
This is probably the skyline that most of you know about Doha.
وهذه على الارجح الافق الذي معظمكم يعرفه عن الدوحه
So what's the population today?
اذا ماهو التعداد اليوم
It's 1.7 million people.
انه 1,7 مليون نسمه
That is in less than 60 years.
حدث هذا في اقل من 60 عاما.
The average growth of our economy is about 15 percent for the past five years.
معدل النمو الاقتصادي حوالي 15 % للسنوات الـ 5 الماضيه
Lifespan has increased to 78.
عمر الانسان ازداد ليصل الى 78
Water consumption has increased to 430 liters.
استهلاك الماء ازداد الى 430 لتر
And this is amongst the highest worldwide.
وهذا يعتبر الاعلى عالميا
From having no water whatsoever
من مرحلة انعدام الماء
to consuming water to the highest degree, higher than any other nation.
الى مرحلة استهلاك الماء الى اعلى معدل , اعلى من اي أمه اخرى.
I don't know if this was a reaction to lack of water.
لا اعلم اذا كان السبب هو ردة فعل تجاه الافتقار الى الماء.
But what is interesting about the story that I've just said?
لكن ماهو المثير للاهتمام في قصتي التي رويتها؟
The interesting part is that we continue to grow
الجزء المثير للاهتمام هو اننا تابعنا النمو
15 percent every year for the past five years without water.
بمعدل 15 % كل عام من الخمس سنوات الماضيه بدون ماء.
Now that is historic. It's never happened before in history.
يعتبر هذا حدث تاريخي ، لم يحدث من قبل في التاريخ
Cities were totally wiped out because of the lack of water.
مدن اختفت بالكامل بسبب شح المياه.
This is history being made in this region.
التاريخ يصنع نفسه في هذه المنطقه
Not only cities that we're building,
انها ليست فقط ما نبنيه من مدن
but cities with dreams and people who are wishing to be scientists, doctors.
ولكنها المدن التي تضم الاحلام والناس الذين يطمحون ليكونوا علماء ودكاتره.
Build a nice home, bring the architect, design my house.
يبنون منازل جميله ، يجلبون المعماريين ، يصممون المنازل.
These people are adamant that this is a livable space when it wasn't.
هؤلاء الناس قرروا بعناد ان هذه المساحه قابله للعيش بينما انها لم تكن كذلك
But of course, with the use of technology.
ولكن بالطبع باستخدام التكنولوجيا
So Brazil has 1,782 millimeters per year of precipitation of rain.
البرازيل يبلغ معدل هطول الامطار السنوي فيها 1,782 ملليميتر
Qatar has 74, and we have that growth rate.
بينما قطر 74 ومع ذلك حققنا هذا المعدل في النمو
The question is how.
السؤال هو
How could we survive that?
كيف استطعنا البقاء هكذا؟
We have no water whatsoever.
بدون اي ماء؟
Simply because of this gigantic, mammoth machine called desalination.
ببساطه بسبب آلات ضخمه يطلق عليها المقطرات
Energy is the key factor here. It changed everything.
الطاقه هي العامل الرئيسي هنا، غيرت كل شئ
It is that thing that we pump out of the ground, we burn tons of,
انها الشئ الذي نضخه من الارض ونقوم بحرق اطنان منه
probably most of you used it coming to Doha.
على الارجح الغالبيه منكم اعتاد القدوم الى الدوحه
So that is our lake, if you can see it.
هذه هي بحيرتنا اذا استطعتم رؤيتها
That is our river.
هذا هو نهرنا.
That is how you all happen to use and enjoy water.
هذا هو السبب في استخدامكم واستمتاعكم بالماء
This is the best technology that this region could ever have: desalination.
هذه افضل تكنولوجيا يمكن لهذه المنطقه ان تمتلكها : المقطرات
So what are the risks?
ماهي المخاطر؟
Do you worry much?
هل تقلقون كثيرا؟
I would say, perhaps if you look at the global facts,
ممكن القول بالنظر الى الوقائع العالميه.
you will realize, of course I have to worry.
سوف تدركون بالطبع انه يجب ان أقلق.
There is growing demand, growing population.
هناك زياده في الاستهلاك زياده في تعداد السكان
We've turned seven billion only a few months ago.
لقد انفقنا سبع مليارات في الاشهر القليله الماضيه.
And so that number also demands food.
وهذا الرقم ايضا لمتطلبات الطعام
And there's predictions that we'll be nine billion by 2050.
وهناك توقع ان هذا سيرتفع الى تسع مليارات بحلول عام 2050
So a country that has no water
ان بلد لايمتلك الماء
has to worry about what happens beyond its borders.
يجب ان يقلق حول الاحداث خارج نطاق حدوده.
There's also changing diets.
و هنك ايضا تغيير في الحمية الغذائية
By elevating to a higher socio-economic level,
و بتحسن الحالة الاقتصادية و الاجتماعية
they also change their diet.
غيروا حميتهمم الغذائية
They start eating more meat and so on and so forth.
بدأوا يأكلون اللحوم أكثر و هلم جرا
On the other hand, there is declining yields
و في المقابل لقد حدث بعض التراجع
because of climate change and because of other factors.
بسبب تغير المناخ و بسبب عوامل اخري
And so someone has to really realize when the crisis is going to happen.
ولذلك علي شخص ما ادراك او معرفة متي ستقع الازمة
This is the situation in Qatar, for those who don't know.
و الموقف في قطر للذي لا يدري منكم, كالتالي
We only have two days of water reserve.
يوجد لدينا من احتياطي الماء يومان فقط
We import 90 percent of our food,
نحن نستورد %90 من غذائنا
and we only cultivate less than one percent of our land.
و نقوم بزرع اقل من %1 من اراضينا.
The limited number of farmers that we have
العدد المحدود من المزراعين لدينا
have been pushed out of their farming practices
تم الدفع بهم خارج اعمالهم
as a result of open market policy and bringing the big competitions, etc., etc.
نتيجة لسياسة السوق المفتوح دخول المنافسين الكبار للسوق الخ,الخ.
So we also face risks.
و لذلك نحن ايضا نواجة المخاطر.
These risks directly affect the sustainability of this nation and its continuity.
هذه المخاطر, تؤثر تأثير مباشر علي بقاء هذة الامة و استمراريتها.
The question is, is there a solution?
و السؤال الذي يطرح نفسة هو, هل هناك حل؟
Is there a sustainable solution?
و هل هناك حل دائم؟
Indeed there is.
في الواقع هناك حل.
This slide sums up thousands of pages of technical documents
و هذة الشريحة تلخص الاف الصفحات من الوثائق التقنية
that we've been working on over the past two years.
هذا ما كنا نعمل علي خلال العامين الماضيين.
Let's start with the water.
دعونا نبدأ بالماء
So we know very well -- I showed you earlier -- that we need this energy.
و من خلال ما اوضحتة سابقا ,نحن نعلم جيدا أننا بحاجة شديدة لهذة الطاقة.
So if we're going to need energy, what sort of energy?
و إذا كانا سنحتاج الطاقة، أي نوع من الطاقة؟
A depletable energy? Fossil fuel?
الوقود الاحفوري؟ الطاقة الدائمة؟
Or should we use something else?
او يجب ان نستخدم شيا آخر؟
Do we have the comparative advantage to use another sort of energy?
هل يوجد لدينا القدرة التنافسية لاستخدام نوع اخر للطاقة؟
I guess most of you by now realize that we do: 300 days of sun.
اعتقد ان الغالبية منكم الان يدركون ان لدينا 300 يوم مشمس
And so we will use that renewable energy to produce the water that we need.
و اننا سنستخدم هذة الطاقة المتجددة لانتاج احتياجتنا من الماء.
And we will probably put 1,800 megawatts of solar systems
و اننا علي الاغلب سنضع 1800 ميجا وات من النظام الشمسي
to produce 3.5 million cubic meters of water.
لانتاج 3.5 مليون مكعب من الماء.
And that is a lot of water.
وهذا ماء كثير.
That water will go then to the farmers,
هذا الماء سيذهب الي المزارعين,
and the farmers will be able to water their plants,
و هؤلاء المزارعين سيكونون قادرين علي رى زرعهم
and they will be able then to supply society with food.
و بالتالي سيقدرون علي تلبية احتياجات المجتمع من الغذاء.
But in order to sustain the horizontal line --
ولكن لكي نحافظ علي ا لخط العرضي
because these are the projects, these are the systems that we will deliver --
لأن هذه هي المشاريع، و النظم التي سنحققها
we need to also develop the vertical line:
ونحتاج ايضا ان نطور الخط الرأسى
system sustenance, high-level education, research and development,
نظام يحافظ علي مستوي عالي في التعليم, البحث و التنمية
industries, technologies, to produce these technologies for application, and finally markets.
الصناعات, التكنولوجيات للتطبيق و اخيرا الاسواق.
But what gels all of it, what enables it, is legislation, policies, regulations.
و لكن ما يربطها و يحققها , هو التشريعات و السياسات و اللوائح.
Without it we can't do anything.
بدونها لا يمكننا عمل اي شيء.
So that's what we are planning to do.
و هذا ما نخطط للقيام به.
Within two years we should hopefully be done with this plan
في غضون سنتين يجب ان نكون انتهينا من وضع هذة الخطة
and taking it to implementation.
و ننتقل بها الي حيز التنفيذ.
Our objective is to be a millennium city, just like many millennium cities around:
أن هدفنا هو ان تكون مدينة الألفية مثل العديد من المدن المحيطة بنا
Istanbul, Rome, London, Paris, Damascus, Cairo.
اسطنبول و روما و لندن وباريس و دمشق و القاهرة.
We are only 60 years old, but we want to live forever
عمر مدينتنا 60 عاما فقط و لكننا نريد العيش للابد
as a city, to live in peace.
كمدينة تعيش في سلام.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا
(Applause)
تصفيق